We started Universal Subtitles because we believe
every video on the web should be subtitle-able.
Millions of Deaf and hard-of-hearing viewers require subtitles to access video.
Videomakers and websites should really care about this stuff too.
Subtitles give them access to a wider audience and they also get better search rankings.
Universal Subtitles makes it incredibly easy to add subtitles to almost any video.
Take an existing video on the web, submit the URL to our website
and then type along with the dialog
to create the subtitles
After that, tap on your keyboard to sync them with the video.
Then you're done— we give you an embed code for the video